Back in 1998, the season of one of the
best Vikings teams in the history of
this organization, Matt Birk was a
sixth-round pick from Harvard and had
quite the illustrious career
establishing himself not only as one of
the best centers in the history of this
football team, but he won a Super
[clears throat] Bowl with the Baltimore
Ravens. U.S. Bank Stadium, welcome Matt
Birk, ladies and gentlemen, joining the
Miller Lite Draft Party Show.
>> Hey Paul, Pete Bercich was on that 1998
team, and Pete, I want you to tell all
the people out there how much did I
contribute
>> [laughter]
>> in 1998?
>> Give it to us. Yeah, quite a bit. Did I?
Oh, yeah. I mean, you gave Morris
something to do.
Right? [laughter] Someone Someone to
mess with, someone to pick on. I was
like the target of his bullying. He was
the sacrificial rookie for John Randle
to do what he needed to do, right?
>> true. True. Yeah, it's a different world
back then. It was different. Do you
remember? It's a that's a tough that's a
tough I mean, not just a tough locker
room, but the meeting room that you
walked into with Randle McDaniel and
Doleman. Todd Steussie. Todd Steussie,
of course.
>> Corey Stringer. And those guys yeah,
those guys And Everett Lindsay. Those
guys were all really easy
>> Corey Whitmer.
>> [laughter]
>> So, you you learn the hard way. Really
nice guys, yeah. Really cared about my
mental [laughter] well-being.
Yeah. Did you Did you like Did you get
the advice of just basically shut your
mouth, keep your head down, and don't
say or do anything until spoken to?
>> Oh, yeah, but I didn't I mean, I didn't
I didn't need that. Like, you we all
knew it. Like, it was like that's just
what you do, especially in in that room.
But, they were I mean, I remember the
first mini camp. Like, Randle McDaniel
was going on, I think, you know, 12 Pro
Bowl in a row. He was just He didn't
want to be there. He was
>> [laughter]
>> He was super bored. Todd Stu- They were
so bored at mini camp. It was like,
"Well, let's just try to make it like
hell for this rookie."
And that's that's what they did.
>> What didn't help you out was the fact
that Todd Steussie was a number He was a
first-round draft pick, right?
>> Yeah. And then you had the Dwayne
Washington thing, so he really wasn't
the first first pick. And then he got He
was brutalized. I mean, I remember as a
rookie cuz I came in with Todd thinking,
"Thank God I am not him in the first
rounder" because he had to pay for
everything. I mean, they just brutalized
him. So, as Fred Zamburlini would say,
"Hurt people hurt people."
>> Yeah. And so, I knew that [laughter]
Steussie, for sure,
would be would be all over you. Steussie
was, and then Randle Mc- You know,
Randle McDaniel everyone's like, "Oh,
Randle McDaniel, he's a great guy." He's
not. He's not.
>> [laughter]
>> He's not a good guy at all. And then And
then that was just getting out of the
Those are the guys kind of on my side,
right? Those are the other alignment.
>> Right. Then you go out on the practice
field, and it's John Randle, and you're
like, Why Of course, I'm crying myself
to sleep every night saying, "I don't I
don't want to do this anymore."
Hey, um hey, how about um this this
change of 8 minutes between each pick? I
mean, we have two picks already. The
Arizona Cardinals have turned in their
pick for pick number three. After them,
the Tennessee Titans.
Anybody with some quick twitch before we
see the commissioner for Arizona at
three? Any uh predictions?
>> Well, this is the first spot where
Jeremiah Love's going to be in play, the
running back for Notre Dame. Many people
think he's the most talented player in
this entire draft, and this is the This
is the high end of of where Jeremiah
Love could go, and you know, they they
do have some running backs, but
Jeremiah Love's going to be special.
>> that you're correct, Charles. I'd say
>> you have reason to believe
>> I have reason to believe Oh, great. We
have pick tippers. Okay, so let's uh
hear the commissioner.
With the third pick in the 2026 NFL
Draft,
the Arizona Cardinals select
Jeremiah Love. All right. Running back,
Notre Dame.
They must have spent 10 million on the
running back room, huh? Yeah, [laughter]
they They brought in Tyler Allgeier,
he's a good back. And they re-signed
James Conner. It doesn't matter. Well,
they threw the ball more than any other
team in the league last year, so they're
they're between one of the three running
backs, they're going to be able to run
it. Doesn't matter who's blocking for
him, right? No, no,
it doesn't matter. All you need is a
good running back. It doesn't You just
put five five doughboys up there and
>> [laughter]
>> it doesn't matter. Hey, uh Matt, uh we
have Matt Birk here, former Vikings
center. Um with um uh with with the
Vikings situation now, it's just it's a
unique situation in that the previous
general manager is gone. There may be a
new general manager in the general
managerial search after the draft.
Meanwhile, the acting general manager
for the Minnesota Viking is somebody
that we know all know quite well. Yeah.
Rob Brzezinski, uh the um you know, the
one of the great money managers,
capologists in the history of the NFL.
So, I just I just wonder how they're
executing this, and uh what do you know
about Rob? Well, I know I used to try to
shake Rob down for a few extra
>> [laughter]
>> pickles
when I was a player. He is He is
fantastic.
>> ever squeeze you?
I think we I don't know. I You'd need to
see if he felt like I squeezed him or he
squeezed me.
He squeezed you, and you laughed.
Um No, I mean, I don't know. I I mean,
you would probably know better than me,
Charles. You're the only guy up here
that hasn't been hit in the head a
bunch.
>> [laughter]
>> Has there ever been a situation like
this where like the general manager was
was let go, and they didn't they did not
hire another general manager to replace
him? No. Let me just I'll just ask that
question. I mean, not
I don't want to say never, but it's it's
very It's very infrequent, and I think
it says a lot about the trust they have
in Rob Brzezinski
>> that they felt like he could he could
execute this moment.
>> If anybody's qualified to run a draft or
run the draft room or whatever it is
without being technically the general
manager, it would Rob Brzezinski would
probably be at the top of the list, but
>> Yeah, that's the thing I'll just kind of
piggyback off of is I've had a lot of
people say like, "Well, explain to me
like why he's qualified." And I was
like, "Well, first of all, have you ever
looked at an NFL coaching staff? You
know how many guys never played football
or didn't play at a high level?"
>> Most. Most, right? Like, That's why
they're coaches. I think there's this
[laughter]
there's this myth and there's like this
misnomer thinking that you have to be a
tried-and-true football guy through and
through to make decisions and/or coach.
>> Case in point. That's just not the case.
Case in point, I've been coaching middle
school football for like 8 years. I'm
pretty sure I have
>> [laughter]
>> pretty sure I have a losing career
record in middle school football.
>> But, I feel like we we should like feel
bad for you now. Who has a kid that
stays in middle school for 8 years?
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, that's crazy.
>> You just don't like recruiting. That's
your problem. I have no budget. I'm I'm
tight with the budget. NIL in middle
school. Now, we're all here We're all
here for the first round, and you get
all the big headlines of the first
rounders. You were a sixth rounder, if I
remember correctly.
>> Weren't you a seventh? Yes, I was a
seventh rounder. So, what I mean, I have
my own version of an answer to this
question, but for someone walking in the
door as a sixth rounder,
that making that from that transition of
being, you know, a guy he's got a chance
if he does X, Y, and Z to become in a
starter, become in a Pro Bowler.
What what what did you do, and what do
you and what do you think of of these
guys you can find in the second and
third day? Listen, I mean, playing
playing in the Ivy League, I mean,
prepared me so well for life in the NFL.
I was ready to go from day
>> [laughter]
>> No, I mean, listen, I think I don't
know. I was just wanted to super happy
to get drafted. Number two, you walk in
as a sixth rounder, like, you're kind of
you're kind of supposed to get cut, you
know? I mean, I mean,
that was kind of nice. Like, there's no
pressure. Of course, I want to make the
team, but nobody's really
they're not expecting a lot out of you.
So, and then you get there, and you're
like, "Holy smokes, I'm in so far over
my head." So,
>> [laughter]
>> it really like
I remember thinking before I got to mini
camp, I'm thinking, "Well, yeah, I want
to play 10 years and do this." And then
you get there, and it's like, "You're
just trying to survive the day." And you
know what though? To be to end up like
You're not You're not I wasn't worried
about down the road. I'm like, "Let me
just try to survive today and get a
little bit better, right?" And like, try
not to get yelled at so much today.
Like, let me try to get my first step
right or do this drill right. And so, I
think actually it sort of just makes you
focus on the now, and you just keep
doing that. And then, you know, kind of
before you know it, you're like, "Okay,
I'm not I'm not half bad" versus like
having these high expectations of
yourself and everybody else. And then,
if things don't go well, you start to
worry about what are people going to
think. And I'm you know, I'm just there
grinding. That's true. I mean, it's it's
only upside cuz it had you come in as a
as the first-round pick, you'd have had
a lot of people looking at you, right? A
lot of fans, I mean, a lot of the
coaches, a lot of the teammates, and it
would have been a little bit of a
different training camp. Obviously,
first-rounders are super talented,
right? But, I mean, the fact that so
many of them don't pan out, it's not I
mean, I think a big part of it is
mental. I mean, it's just there's a lot
going especially I mean, every year it's
more and more and more. It just seems
like, you know, like the the the weight
of the franchises is on their shoulders,
and that's a that's a for a
21-22-year-old kid. So, your first
training camp, Matt, you're you're
you're you're the sixth rounder, and I'm
sure the whole time you're like, "Am I
going to get cut? Am I going to get cut?
Am I going to get cut?" Were I was
pretty sure I was getting cut. I wasn't
asking. I was like, Yeah, you're
>> [laughter]
>> like, "I'm just waiting."
>> Today? No, not today.
All right. So, tell me Well, tell me
about cutdown day then, right? And
then there's a couple of cutdown days. I
mean, are you just on pins and needles
waiting for the phone call and turning
in your playbook? Well, what happened
for me, you know, big veteran group, and
then Mike Tice was my O-line coach. You
know, I don't know if you remember Mike
Tice, but
>> Of course. He kind [laughter] of He kind
of tell you exactly
what it was like at that moment. So, it
was like, "You're going to get cut.
You're getting cut." And then, we had a
scrimmage against the Kansas City Chiefs
over in River Falls.
>> Oh, yeah. Those were epic. Lot of
fights. I don't know what happened. If
it I just kind of said, "Enough's
enough, but whatever." But, I just kind
of had this really great scrimmage,
Time. Tennessee Titans, fourth. Roger
Goodell, Mendoza, Bailey, and Jeremiah
Love have gone. Here come the Titans.
With the fourth pick in the 2026 NFL
Draft,
the Tennessee Titans select
Cardale Tate.
Wide receiver,
Ohio State. How about that for the first
surprise Oh, okay. That's cool. So, uh
the New York Giants, which is going to
be my final question, involves the
Giants for Birkie. Uh they're next, to
first of two picks, uh five and 10
because of a Dexter Lawrence trade to
Cincinnati. Finish the story, please.
Well, no, I just kind of something
clicked over there. Remember we doing
one-on-ones and
um I had to go against Chester
McGlockton and I'm not saying I'm not
saying big Chester was like super
motivated at that
>> [laughter]
>> at that time, but
I kind of locked him down and then and
then Mike Tyson sort of called he kind
of called out the Chiefs D-line was
like, "This guy's a rookie, you know,
someone else go." I remember I did like
seven one-on-ones in a row and I like
won every one of them. It's something
just kind of clicked, you know, and
maybe for me it was that click was like,
"Hey, I think I can actually do this."
Um
but you know, kind of took it and pushed
to the brink of you know, like a like a
like a mental breakdown
>> [laughter]
>> to to get there. And so after that after
that Chiefs scrimmage I kind of I you
know, I was I I sort of said, "Okay,
I felt like if I just keep working hard
and do the right things that that things
are going to work out."
>> lastly, uh your former coach with the
Baltimore Ravens, somebody with whom you
won a Super Bowl, somebody I know you
admire greatly, John Harbaugh, has two
uh two picks coming up here, five and
10. What was it like playing for Harbs?
And um and as a center as part of an
offense for him, Joe Flacco the
quarterback, the whole thing. If he's
looking offense, like what does he like
stylistically offensively?
>> playing for Harbs is great. I mean,
probably great you look back on it you
say it was better than it was. He's just
one of those guys that somehow he just
he can kind of get you to do way more
than you want to do, but you but you but
you still actually respect him and like
him. Um and obviously a great coach.
He's a great leader. I mean, to play
offense for Harbs
listen, that was Harbs' second year as a
head coach. I knew more about offense
than Harbs did.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, special teams defensive guy. It's
great. Uh but Harbs has I mean, he's
he's just got a real uh clear vision of
what he wants his team to look like. Uh
Harbs I don't know much about the
Giants. I they're going to either draft
an O-lineman, a D-lineman, or a or a
D-back.
That's what Harbs loves and they're
going to be they're going to be physical
players.
>> It'll lead into uh US Bank Stadium, one
of the great centers in the history of
Minnesota Vikings football and a Super
Bowl champion. Round of applause for
Matt Birk, ladies and gentlemen. See
you, Birk. You're fantastic, Birk.